Abraham: As we all know the internet
is available almost everywhere and
can connect people all over the world,
but this makes it very hard to police.
Nicole: Threats can come from anywhere
and tracking the threat actors down
can be very difficult especially when
they are acting in another country.
Abraham: It is for this reason that
cyberspace would benefit from being
regulated by international law but how
this could be done is a real challenge
especially as many nation states
have differing views on the subject.
Nicole: There are currently no clear
answers on how this could be facilitated
but there are some clear trends.
Some states are in favour of creating
international institutions like the United
Nations, set up to regulate cyberspace,
other think it should remain unregulated.
Many nation states feel that they should
be able to apply their own regulations.
Abraham: In 2015 all the 193 members
of the United Nations, agreed
that international Law should
apply in cyberspace, but how these
laws should be implemented and
negotiated is still up for debate.
Nicole: Different nations interpret
how to apply international laws in
different ways as they interpret
other laws in different ways.
Abraham: It has become evident over the
last few years that many nation states see
the use of cyberspace differently and some
offer more freedom to its use than others.
Some see ‘digital mass surveillance’
as a violation of human rights,
but others see it as a way of
monitoring the population and helping
to maintain a peaceful society!
Nicole: What happens if one state
‘hacks” another state, does that
mean that they have the right
of self-defence to hack back?
Who is going to police this?
There are some organisations other
than the UN out there trying to
resolve these problems such as:
Abraham: The Paris Call for Trust and
Security in Cyberspace who invited
states and the private sector, the
world of research and civil society
to work together to adopt fundamental
principles and responsible behaviour.
Nicole: The Cybersecurity Tech
Accord which works to foster
collaboration amongst global companies
to defend themselves from threat.
Abraham: The Global Commission on
the Stability of Cyberspace which
includes international governments,
businesses and organisations helps to
promote awareness and understanding
on issues of cyber security.
Nicole: Many similarly minded countries
show a willingness to get together
to address the goal of creating
international laws and regulations
in cyberspace but unless some of the
other major players get on board this
has little chance of becoming law.
However, some individual countries
feel that they should have the right
to control their own cyberspace free
from international interference.
Abraham: Some of these countries
are large players in cyberspace such
as Russia, China and Saudi Arabia.
This can be seen quite clearly
with the current global unrest
issues which are changing the
face of cyberspace in the world.
Nicole: Some countries also want
to have more control over digital
monopolies and be able to regulate and
tax some of the larger tech companies.
Some governments also want tech
companies and internet service providers
to restrict and monitor some content
whilst still offering freedom of speech.
Abraham: Net neutrality is
also a cause for concern.
It means that internet service
providers must treat all content
flowing through their systems the same.
Companies shouldn’t be able to block
access to any services and should
keep the internet as an open field
which is crucial for innovation.
Nicole: Zero rating on the other hand is
the practice of providing free internet
services under certain conditions.
There are no current international laws
covering ‘Net neutrality’ and ‘zero
rating’ but many feel these fall into
the category of ‘human rights laws’ which
apply to many countries around the world.
Abraham: We seem a long way off from
having an international cyberspace
law as it stands today and if every
country or nation state has its own
laws then it would be practically
impossible to prosecute anyone
for international cyber crimes.
Nicole: So, as you can see the
whole debate about international
laws and cyberspace is rather
a tangled web, pardon the pun.